A Guide to John Henry Ingram's Poe Collection
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Part One: Letters, Manuscripts, Other Documents
  - REVEREND JOHN HENRY HOPKINS, JR., Plattsburg, NY, ALS to MARIE LOUISE SHEW HOUGHTON, 1875 February 9.; [201]; 4 pp. (Box 4)
    Enclosed in Item 197. Hopkins tried to persuade Poe in 1848 to omit pantheistic elements from his Eureka, but Poe refused, saying, "My whole nature utterly revolts at the idea that there is any Being in the Universe superior to myself!" He and Dr. Roland S. Houghton on one occasion found Poe "crazy-drunk" and took him home to Fordham, leaving $5 with Maria Clemm for immediate necessities. Poe thought that the Jesuit fathers at Fordham College were highly cultivated gentlemen and scholars because they smoked, drank, and played cards like gentlemen and never said a word about religion.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 February 14.; [202]; 12 pp. (Box 4)
    Anna Blackwell, not Elizabeth, boarded with Maria Clemm at Fordham to rest from her literary labors, the cottage having been recommended by Mary Gove Nichols, who headed a water-cure establishment in New York. It was Anna, who seems not to have been friendly to Poe, who gave Mrs. Whitman Poe's letter to her of 14 June 1848. Mrs. Whitman is certain that Ingram printed nothing without her implied authority. Mentions: articles in the Examiner, the Saturday Review, the Spectator; William F. Gill's blunders with the Poe materials he received from Mrs. Whitman; Richard Henry Stoddard's Philobiblion article on Poe; another in Hearth and Home by A. B. Harris.
  - ELIZABETH OAKES SMITH, Hollywood, NC, ALS toINGRAM, 1875 February 25.; [203]; 2 pp. (Box 4)
    Poe was chameleon-like, taking on his coloring from those about him. Mrs. Oakes Smith encloses her thirty-page sketch of Poe.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 March 9.; [204]; 4 pp. (Box 4)
    A friend has dissuaded Caleb Fiske Harris from paying $50 for the 1829 edition of Poe's poems. Harris will send his copy of the 1831 edition to Ingram within a fortnight.
  - MARY GOVE NICHOLS, Malvern, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 March 10.; [205]; 3 pp. (Box 4)
    Marie Louise Barney married first Dr. Joel Shew, then Dr. Roland Houghton. Poe went intoxicated to Sarah Helen Whitman's home, followed by a crowd of boys, which caused his engagement to her to be broken. Mrs. Whitman took money from her mother to pay his way out of town.
  - REVEREND JOHN HENRY HOPKINS, Plattsburg, NY, ALS to MARIE LOUISE SHEW HOUGHTON, 1875 March 10.; [206]; 2 pp. (Box 4)
    Enclosed in Item 226. Hopkins remembers Thomas Dunn English as a scoundrel. He has written Dr. Caleb Sprague Henry, editor of the New York Review, to inquire about Poe's connection with that publication.
  - CALEB S. HENRY, Stamford, CT, ALS to REVEREND JOHN HENRY HOPKINS, 1875 March 13.; [207]; 1 p. (Box 4)
    Enclosed in Item 226. Poe never was "engaged as a writer on the New York Review"; he contributed one article on his own account.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 March 26.; [208]; 4 pp. (Box 4)
    Caleb Fiske Harris has sent Ingram his copy of the 1831 edition of Poe's poems. Edmund Gosse's criticism of Poe's poetry in the Examiner (27 January 1875) is presumptuous; he would appreciate "Ulalume" if he understood its weird symbolism. Mentions: Ingram's article in the International Review and the Athenaeum's notice of his edition of Poe's works.
  - E. DORA HOUGHTON, The Chestnuts, Whitestone, NY, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 March 26 and 29.; [209]; 4 pp. (Box 4)
    Mary Star was loyal to Poe and Maria Clemm, but Poe spoke of her with scorn as being married to a merchant-tailor and content with her lot.
  - MARIE LOUISE SHEW HOUGHTON, Flushing, NY, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 March 28.; [210]; 10 pp. (Box 4)
    Because everyone knew who it was Poe had praised so extravagantly in "To M. L. S--," Mrs. Houghton did not want him to publish "The Beloved Physician." Rufus Griswold wanted it at one time, and if he got it he must have suppressed it out of enmity to her. Mrs. Houghton encloses MSS. of "To Marie Louise" and another valentine Poe sent to her "a year" later. The day before she died, Virginia Poe took a worn letter from her portfolio, written by the second Mrs. Allan, in which she acknowledged that she alone had been responsible for John Allan's neglect of Poe because she thought Poe really might be blood kin to Allan. Griswold must have gotten this letter along with Poe's other papers. She has found in a vase some leaves from the journal she kept while Poe was sick. Poe laughed at the perplexity people showed over the identity of the persons to whom his poems were written.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 March 30.; [211]; 4 pp. (Box 4)
    Mrs. Whitman does not object to her book Edgar Poe and His Critics being called her "finest poem." She cautions Ingram to keep cool and not to provoke a fight with Richard Henry Stoddard. Last week's Nation has critical reviews of both Ingram's and Stoddard's Memoirs of Poe. John Russell Bartlett has made a copy of Anna Blackwell's letter from Poe; Mrs. Whitman will copy it verbatim for Ingram [Item 33]. Maria Clemm did not mention Marie Louise Shew Houghton to Mrs. Whitman.
  - THOMAS LOW NICHOLS, Malvern, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 April 3.; [212]; 3 pp. (Box 4)
    Nichols returns Richard Henry Stoddard's book which he thinks a shabby and nasty biography.
  - MARIE LOUISE SHEW HOUGHTON, Flushing, NY, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 April 3.; [213]; 18 pp. (Box 4)
    Poe was mortified over Maria Clemm's accepting money from Sarah Anna Lewis, which obliged him to praise her verse in print; he fled the house to escape her. He had a bundle of his mother's letters and two sketches, one of Boston harbor, 1808; Mrs. Clemm gave them to Rosalie Poe. Poe's estimate of John Henry Hopkins was wrong. Mrs. Clemm dressed very plainly, lectured her hostess, and worshiped the world; had she not covered over many things, many charitable persons in New York would willingly have helped save Poe. Mrs. Houghton has a picture very like the side view she had copied of Elizabeth Poe. Poe carefully wrote into Mrs. Houghton's album the verse "Like All True Souls of Noble Birth," sent to her by Mary Gove Nichols. She has two of Poe's letters to her. He always treated her with respect, but he was "so excentric [sic] and so unlike others" that she was forced "to define a position I was bound to take." A man named Jones came to her house recently asking to buy Poe biographical materials. She encloses a letter from Annie Richmond to her in which Mrs. Clemm is described as treacherous and cruel.
  - ELIZABETH OAKES SMITH, Hollywood, NC, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 April 7.; [214]; 8 pp. (Box 4)
    Poe suffered from "mental isolation, living in dreams and bewildered by the real." He saw nothing wrong in his fulsome praise of Sarah Anna Lewis's poetry, since he was indebted to her. Maria Clemm engineered his marriage to Virginia to keep him from marrying Eliza White, who was capricious and addicted to morphia; but to Poe women were no more than a dream. He appeared to be faithful to Virginia during her lifetime. Rufus Griswold said that Poe left a bushel basket of letters addressed to him by women. He, Griswold, returned Elizabeth F. Ellet's letters to her. Thomas W. White distrusted Poe and was irritated by him. It was said that Poe had tried to seduce his stepmother, the second Mrs. Allan.
  - MARIE LOUISE SHEW HOUGHTON, Flushing, NY, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 April 9.; [215]; 12 pp. (Box 4)
    John Henry Hopkins has returned forty pages of her journal which contain Poe's accounts of having been wounded in a duel in a foreign port, of having written a sensational novel called "Life of an Artist at Home and Abroad," which was later credited to Eugene Sue, and a poem called "Humanity," credited to George Sand, and of having been nursed by a Scottish lady to whom he wrote a poem entitled "Holy Eyes." He wrote "The Beloved Physician" two months after Virginia's death. Poe said that his brother was a dashing cavalier with more of the Poe nature than he himself had. Mrs. Houghton is suspicious and antagonistic toward Sarah Anna Lewis.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 April 14.; [216]; 4 pp. (Box 4)
    Mrs. Whitman finds Ingram's article on the philosophy of handwriting very piquant and entertaining; his article on Poe in the March International will live while Poe's memory endures. She remarks that Ingram has found Mary Gove Nichols "fanciful."
  - GEORGE LONG, Porterfield, Chichester, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 April 15.; [217]; 4 pp. (Box 4)
    Long, Professor of Ancient Languages at the University of Virginia in 1826, vaguely remembers Poe as being "not among the worst and among the best" students. He remarks on the faculty-student trouble during the first year of the University. Mentions: William Wertenbaker, Robert M. T. Hunter, Henry Tutwiler, and Gessner Harrison.
  - MARIE LOUISE SHEW HOUGHTON, Flushing, NY, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 ca. April 15.; [218]; 12 pp. (Box 4)
    Mrs. Houghton has sent copies of his works that Poe gave her. The miniature of his mother was left in his satchel on the Baltimore train. She had copied this miniature on ivory, and that copy is now in the possession of one of her children. Poe once attended church services with her. During the first part he followed the service and sang the psalms, but he became excited and rushed out. At the end of the service he reappeared. After that, he called on Dr. William Augustus Muhlenberg, the pastor. Mrs. Houghton offers to give Sarah Helen Whitman the jewel case that had belonged to Poe's mother.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 April 27.; [219]; 4 pp. (Box 4)
    Mrs. Whitman thinks Ingram's article on Poe in the Civil Service Review, ca. 1 April 1875, tears Richard Henry Stoddard's Memoir of Poe to shreds, but she fears it will cause trouble, since Stoddard controls the New York Tribune. She feels, too, that Ingram has brought her too openly in conflict with Stoddard. The two parodies of "The Bells" were by different writers. Letter encloses Item 603, a tribute to the late Colonel Gamaliel Lyman Dwight.
  - JOHN PRENTISS POE, Baltimore, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 May 1.; [220]; 6 pp. (Box 4)
    Responds to Ingram's interest in Poe genealogy. Poe says that there is no good reason to suppose that Edgar was descended from the De La Poers. Poe's brother was said to be a poet of genius. Maria Clemm was married only once. Virginia Clemm was born in Baltimore on 13 August 1822 and married Edgar on 16 March 1836.
  - MARIE LOUISE SHEW HOUGHTON, Flushing, NY, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 May 2 and 3.; [221]; 7 pp. (Box 4)
    Mrs. Houghton has sent Ingram a daguerreotype of Poe and a note from Poe to Virginia. She is moving from Flushing to Whitestone, Long Island.
  - EDWARD V. VALENTINE, Richmond, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 May 4.; [222]; 4 pp. (Box 4)
    Valentine declines either to give or to post Ingram's letter to Mrs. John Allan because the subject of Edgar is disagreeable to her. She has stated that she saw Poe only once or twice and that she did not know him when he called at the Allan house. Ingram's letter to Sarah Elmira Royster Shelton has been left where it can be sent to her.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 May 7.; [223]; 8 pp. (Box 4)
    Mrs. Whitman thinks that Elizabeth Oakes Smith's story about Eliza White is without foundation. Paulina Davis told Mrs. Whitman of Marie Louise Shew Houghton's admirably appointed water-cure establishment in upper New York. She suggests that Ingram consider carefully before reprinting the copies of Poe's letters sent by Mrs. Houghton because they lack his characteristic style.
  - JOHN NEAL, Portland, ME, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 May 10.; [224]; 4 pp. (Box 4)
    Neal has given away his Poe autographed letters. He either never knew or has forgotten that Poe dedicated his Tamerlane to him. He wrote the first praise Poe received in a notice in the Yankee in September 1829 and wrote another notice in December quoting selected lines from Poe's poems.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 May 11.; [225]; 5 pp. (Box 4)
    William F. Gill has sent Mrs. Whitman a revised edition of his Lotos Leaves containing his article on Poe. She urges caution in Ingram's accepting as Poe's all that is sent to him as unpublished writings, especially "copies." Something about the reported poem "The Beloved Physician" is "not quite... vraisemblable." Mentions: unfavorable criticism of Ingram's Memoir in the Nation; Mary Gove Nichols being imaginative; Caleb Fiske Harris having sent to Ingram both the 1829 and the 1845 editions of Poe's poems; Anna Blackwell witnessing spiritualistic phenomena in the presence of Hume; Ingram's remark that George R. Graham's letters have replaced Rufus Griswold's Memoir in a new American edition of Poe's works.
  - MARIE LOUISE SHEW HOUGHTON, Whitestone, NY, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 May 16.; [226]; 16 pp. (Box 4)
    Ingram is not to let the Poe family know that he has the miniature of Elizabeth Poe and is to try to get the one Poe had with him when he died. Maria Clemm burned a package of Mrs. Houghton's letters to Poe. Poe spent a year abroad and never betrayed his whereabouts to anyone. Only Virginia knew how he got the scar on his left shoulder. Mrs. Clemm used Mrs. Houghton only when she needed protection and money. It was Mary Gove Nichols who sent her to visit the Poe family. Friends wondered that she was not afraid of Poe. Poe's cat ("Caterina") seemed to be possessed; it would not eat when he was absent and was found dead when Mrs. Clemm returned to Fordham for her last load of boxes. Mrs. Houghton says that she had promised Virginia Poe that she would listen patiently to Poe's lamentation, and Mrs. Clemm reproved her for indulging Poe in his fancies. Mentions: Sarah Anna Lewis being old and ugly, David Poe's faithfulness to his wife, Poe's belief that he owed his gifts of intellect and heart to his mother, and his statement that he had burned the sweetest poem he ever wrote in order to conciliate Mrs. Clemm and his father's family.
  - JOHN PARKER, Peabody Institute, Baltimore, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 May 17.; [227]; 4 pp. (Box 4)
    Professor J. A. Anthony says that Thomas Wyatt paid Poe for the use of his name as author of a book on conchology because he had been unable to sell his original book on the subject. Francis B. Davidge edited the Baltimore Minerva between 1830 and 1835. Eugene L. Didier of Baltimore is collecting materials and writing about Poe.
  - EDWARD V. VALENTINE, Richmond, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 May 18.; [228]; 4 pp. (Box 4)
    Valentine encloses an extract of a letter from Dr. Richard Carey Ambler of Richmond who swam with Poe in Shockoe Creek. Poe wrote a satire in verse on a debating society. Rosalie Poe gave a likeness of Poe to Dr. Claude Baxley. There was trouble between Poe and Thomas W. White about copy for the Southern Literary Messenger.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 May 27.; [229]; 6 pp. (Box 4)
    Ingram has been invited to the semi-centennial celebration of the University of Virginia. Marie Louise Shew Houghton has written to Mrs. Whitman protesting Ingram's crediting Sarah Anna Lewis with service which Mrs. Houghton had performed for the Poe family; Mrs. Whitman does not like the tone of the letter and thinks the "Rival Queens" might get Ingram into trouble. Mentions: Maria Clemm's long visits in the homes of the Lewis family and of Mrs. Houghton, Mrs. Mary Higgins Macready's claim that she received "The Fire Fiend" from Mrs. Clemm as an unpublished poem by Poe, and Ingram's review of Henry Curwen's Sorrow and Song.
  - OSSIAN E. DODGE, London, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 June 1.; [230]; 2 pp. (Box 4)
    Dodge offers to show Ingram a daguerreotype of Poe.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, AL to INGRAM, 1875 June 2.; [231]; Fragment. 6 pp. (Box 4)
    Samuel Stillman Osgood's portrait of Poe created the false impression of weakness in his mouth and chin. Richard Henry Stoddard's article about Poe's mendacity was in the Aldine in the spring of 1873. Mrs. Whitman quotes from Stoddard's letter to her apologizing for appearing to have discredited her statements in Edgar Poe and His Critics. She does not wish to be drawn into a conflict with him. Mrs. Whitman has received another letter from Marie Louise Shew Houghton in which she makes "rash charges" against Maria Clemm and Sarah Anna Lewis. William F. Gill has asserted that he furnished Ingram with facts for his Memoir of Poe.
  - MARIE LOUISE SHEW HOUGHTON, Whitestone, NY, AL to INGRAM, 1875 June 7.; [232]; Fragment. 3 pp. (Box 4)
    Mrs. Houghton thinks the MS. of "The Beloved Physician" is in a desk in Pierrepont Manor, 300 miles away. Her son Henry says that Poe cut it down to nine stanzas for publication. She promises the MS. of the poem and a letter in which Poe mentions it for Ingram's use in his Memoir of Poe.
  - ELIZABETH OAKES SMITH, Hollywood, NC, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 June 8.; [233]; 6 pp. (Box 4)
    Rufus Griswold's last years were without dignity or happiness. Alice Cary, Mary E. Hewitt, and Mary Bean championed him; Sarah Anna Lewis, Ann S. Stephens, and Elizabeth F. Ellet pursued him with malice. Poe lived unhappily with Mrs. Lewis for a part of one summer. He was not a lover in the common sense, for his feelings toward women were totally of an ideal kind. Mentions: Mary Gove Nichols, Eliza White, and Sarah Helen Whitman.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 June 25.; [234]; 6 pp. (Box 4)
    Mrs. Whitman is pleased that Ingram is to visit the United States in the autumn. Jane E. Locke has been dead for many years; Poe was her guest in Lowell in the autumn of 1848, and it was she who introduced him to Annie Richmond. Anne Lynch Botta is eminently practical, enterprising, prudent, circumspect, and cautious.
  - WILLIAM HAND BROWNE, Baltimore, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 June.; [235]; 4 pp. (Box 4)
    Edward V. Valentine's recumbent statue of General Lee has been unveiled, and the public schools in Baltimore plan to erect a monument to Poe. Maria Clemm was one of those gentle, childlike, weak women whom you could not help loving but losing all patience with. However, a Southerner, remembering the war, must not speak ill of a Southern woman, for what they endured is beyond belief.
  - EDWARD V. VALENTINE, Richmond, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 July 2.; [236]; 12 pp. (Box 4)
    Valentine copies for Ingram a long account, almost certainly the joint work of Mrs. Ellis and Mary Jane Poitiaux Dixon of Richmond, which states that Poe's mother died in 1813, casts doubt upon Rosalie Poe's legitimacy, and claims that Poe was a mischievous youth, that he ran up debts in Charlottesville for champagne and broadcloth coats which he later gambled away, and that he attempted to force his way into John Allan's sickroom. Sarah Elmira Royster Shelton was engaged to marry Poe in 1849, and she gave him money to bear his expenses to Baltimore. Valentine repeats a rumor that Elizabeth Poe died in a poorhouse. He also sends a copy of her obituary in the Richmond Enquirer, 10 December 1811.
  - MARY JANE POITIAUX DIXON, Richmond, to MESSRS. EDITORS, 1875 July 2.; [237]; MS. 6 pp. (Box 4)
    As a youth Poe wrote doggerel lines and was adept in athletic sports. He told her on his last visit to Richmond that he had written "The Raven" while on the verge of delirium tremens. He had been alternately petted and punished in his early life.
  - JOHN PARKER, Peabody Institute, Baltimore, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 July 7.; [238]; 6 pp. (Box 4)
    Professor J. A. Anthony has learned that for the abridgment of The Conchologist's First Book the name of "some irresponsible person" was needed whom it would be idle to sue for damages. Poe was selected and paid for the use of his name.
  - EDWARD V. VALENTINE, Richmond, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 July 20.; [239]; 6 pp. (Box 4)
    Sarah Elmira Royster Shelton is reported to be denying that she was either engaged to marry Poe or that she wore mourning after his death. Thomas Bolling of Nelson County, VA, has written that Poe was an excellent athlete, that he used his fine talent for drawing by filling the space in his dormitory room at the University of Virginia and by copying a life-sized drawing of Byron on the ceiling, and that he also had a habit of listening to a conversation and dividing his mind by writing sense on a different subject. Copies of Al Aaraaf were on sale in a Richmond bookstore.
  - JOHN PARKER, Peabody Institute, Baltimore, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 July 28.; [240]; 3 pp. (Box 4)
    William Gilmore Simms' novel Beauchampe was based on an account of an actual execution found in Lewis Collins' History of Kentucky (Covington, 1874) 1: 32.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 August 10.; [241]; 10 pp. (Box 4)
    Mrs. Whitman discusses daguerreotypes of Poe made in Providence in 1848. She understands that Ingram has discouraged her from detailing for him any more of her personal experiences with Poe because she does not wish them to be published. She assures Ingram that she is profoundly interested in his work and that she has genuine personal sympathy and affectionate regard for him. Mentions: Richard Henry Stoddard as the author of those "dastardly articles" in the Round Table, the MS. of the second "To Helen" that she had sent to Professor Joseph Rhodes Buchanan for a psychometric reading, an article on Poe in the British Quarterly for July, and how she is sometimes "very anxious" to escape "this fever called living."
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, letter to INGRAM. Note appended to INGRAM from ROSE PECKHAM, dated 15 August., 1875 August 13.; [242]; Copy by Ingram. 2 pp. (Box 5)
    Mrs. Whitman thinks that the article on Poe in the British Quarterly is the best critique on his life and genius that she has seen, and she anxiously inquires the name of the author. [Dr. Alexander Hay Japp had written the article.] Mrs. Whitman expresses her doubt of the good will of Poe's relatives. Ingram adds a note: "Original to Dr. Japp, 2/3/80."
  - WILLIAM HAND BROWNE, Baltimore, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 August 17.; [243]; 4 pp. (Box 5)
    Browne asks whether Alfred, Lord Tennyson would write a poem or a few verses for reading at the ceremony when Poe's monument is unveiled. Poe loved Virginia and was faithful to her, although his dangerous power over women subjected him to great temptations. Rufus Griswold married for money, divorced, and remarried, but the decree of divorce was reversed, and he was sued for bigamy, but he died before the suit came to trial. Poe's criticism of Richard Henry Horne's Orion was careless and full of errors.
  - ELIZABETH OAKES SMITH, Hollywood, NC, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 September 8.; [244]; 2 pp. (Box 5)
    Mrs. Oakes Smith requests the return of her MS. article on Poe. She says that Elizabeth F. Ellet, who is not to be trusted, gave Sarah Anna Lewis "a blighting name." Mentions Mrs. Lewis' drama Sappho.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 September 28.; [245]; 8 pp. (Box 5)
    Mrs. Whitman thinks that Eugene L. Didier's publication of "Alone" in Scribner's for September, as a facsimile of a poem by Poe, an audacious forgery, although the poem itself might be readily accepted as genuine. [See Item 611.] She discusses at length Francis Gerry Fairfield's article on Poe, "A Mad Man of Letters," in Scribner's for October. Mrs. Whitman shares Ingram's lack of confidence in Neilson Poe. Mentions: William F. Gill, Richard Henry Stoddard, Thomas C. Clarke.
  - EDWARD V. VALENTINE, Richmond, ALS to INGRAM, 1875 October 1.; [246]; 2 pp. (Box 5)